Dr. William Benjamin Worth Watkins papers, Inclusive: 1884-1918, undated, Bulk: 1884-1888
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Dr. William Benjamin Worth Watkins papers
Inclusive: 1884-1918, undated, Bulk: 1884-1888
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
3807
Bach, Cynthia Watkins
1 document box.
The Dr. William Benjamin Worth Watkins papers consist of correspondence by Dr. Watkins and Nancy Ellen Taylor. The majority of the letters are between Dr. Watkins and Nancy Ellen Taylor, who married in 1884.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Unknown.
Biography/Profile
Dr. William Benjamin Worth Watkins first began courting Nancy Ellen “Nellie” Taylor in 1884. The two later married on 1884 August 7. From 1887-88, Watkins went to Nashville, Tennessee, for medical school, while Nancy stayed at their home in Eureka, Texas. They wrote to each other often during that year that they were apart. In 1908, Dr. Watson again traveled away from Nancy for “lung treatments” in Corpus Christi, Texas. The couple had two children who survived to adulthood, their son Mortimer J. and daughter Aubre. Mortimer went overseas during World War I and corresponded with his mother until his death in 1918, probably due to the war. Dr. Watkins died in 1915.
Scope and Content
The Dr. William Benjamin Worth Watkins papers contain handwritten letters between the couple, to and from their children, to and from Taylor family members, and to various friends. Clippings that were sent with the letters but not attached to specific letters are placed together at the end. The family history is documented in the genealogy portion which contains a family tree, photographs, page from the family Bible, and biographical information about the Taylor family.
Many of the manuscripts are love letters between Dr. Watkins and Nancy Ellen Taylor Watkins. The letters provide an excellent picture of a family in Texas during the late 1800s and during World War I.
Nancy Ellen “Nellie” Taylor wrote to her son Mortimer J. Watkins for three months after his demise in 1918 August. She had not received word back from him or about him and thus continued to write letters to him until 1918 November. In 1918 November, Nancy Ellen Taylor received a returned letter with the word, “Deceased” written on the front of the envelope of a letter she had sent to her son. This letter can be found in Folder 6 of Box 1.
Arrangement
This collection contains only one series, Correspondence. The Dr. William Benjamin Worth Watkins papers begin with handwritten correspondence followed by clippings and family genealogy. The letters had no prior organization prior to this finding aid.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 3807. Acquired 2012-05-23
Index Terms
Places
Texas -- History -- 1846-1950.
Subjects
Genealogy.; World War, 1914-1918 -- United States.
Genres
Correspondence.
- Correspondence, 1884-1918, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Unknown.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains letters, clippings, and family genealogy materials. This series is in good condition.
  - From Dr. W.B.W. Watkins to Nancy Ellen Taylor, 1884 February 27-July 21 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - From Dr. W.B.W. Watkins to Nancy Ellen Taylor, 1884 July 26- December 24 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - From Dr. W.B.W. Watkins to Nancy Ellen Taylor, 1888 December 24- January 14 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - From Dr. W.B.W. Watkins to Nancy Ellen Taylor, 1888, 1908, 1915, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - From Nancy Ellen Taylor to Dr. W.B.W. Watkins, 1887 December 13- 1888 February 17 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Between Nancy Ellen Taylor and Mortimer J. Watkins, 1916, 1918 May- November 22, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - From Taylor Family Members to Dr. W.B.W. Watkins, 1883, 1887 July 18- 1888 January 31 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence, 1887, 1894, 1902, 1905, 1915, 1918, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Prose, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Family Genealogy, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)